All those ones and zeroes flying by, all those bits
“你好 世界”
Hello world.
你好 世界
现在我们发出的是信号还是噪音？
Is it signal, or is it noise?
我们日日夜夜无休止地写代码
All the work we do as developers,
做测试工作
all the countless hours of coding and stressing and testing,
我们追求的事情只有一个
it all comes down to that one question:
我们是否传递了我们的信号？
are we getting our signal across?
你好
Hello
或者我们的信号是不是丢失了？
Or is our signal lost?
难道我们一直在制造无意义的杂音吗？*噪音*
Are we just making noise.
我是 Saron Yitbarek，这是代码英雄第二季
I'm Saron Yitbarek and this is season two of Command Line Heroes,
来自红帽原创播客
an original podcast from Red Hat.
今天的话题将在“翻译”中挖掘
In today's episode we're found in translation.
这关于编程语言的故事：
It's all about programming languages:
它们是怎么来的 如何选择其中一个语言来学习
where they came from, and how we choose which ones to learn.
我们将深入研究如何与机器对话
We're doing a deep dive into the ways we talk to our machines.
探究这些语言是如何演化的
How those languages are evolving.
以及我们如何用它们来让我们的工作变得更好
And how we can use them to make our work sing.
Daisy daisy  来告诉我你的正确回答
Daisy, daisy, give me your answer true.
如果你像我一样是一个开发者
你可能也经受着去精通多种语言的压力
you probably feel pressure to be a polyglot, to be fluent in a whole bunch of languages.
最起码你得会 Java 更好一些得懂 Python、
You better know Java. Better know Python.
Go、JavaScript、Node
甚至能够用 C++ 思考
也许为了增加可信度
可能你还要熟悉古典的 COBOL
甚至你还得学点新东西
And you might even be worrying about a newcomer,
比如 Dart 实在太累了
like Dart... It's exhausting.
奇怪的是
The weird thing is,
我们正在讨论的计算机只讲一种语言：
the computers that we're talking to really only speak one language:
机器语言
machine language.
以二进制形式飘过的 1 和 0
All those ones and zeroes flying by, all those bits
说到底 Every single language we learn is,
我们学习的每个语言都是殊途同归
at the end of the day, just another pathway to the same place.
不管有多抽象
It all gets boiled down,
它都是用来简化我们工作的道具
no matter how abstracted we are when we're doing the work.
这就是我希望你们记住的 故事开始了
And that's what I want you to keep in mind as our story begins,
从那一刻
because we're starting with the moment,
那一个经典辉煌的时刻
the completely brilliant moment,
一个女人说：“你知道么？
when one woman said: "You know what?
我是人类 我不想用二进制来讨论思考
I'm a human. I don't talk in bits, I don't think in bits.
我就想用英语去编程。”
I want to program using English words."
在今天可能看来是一个简单的概念
Might seem like a simple concept today,
但曾几何时
but once upon a time,
使用人类的方式与计算机对话这个主意 - 说轻点是一个笑话
that idea, the idea you should be able to talk to a computer in your own way was a joke at best,
严重点就是亵渎
sacrilege at worst.
代码英雄第二季 将讲述成就我们基础的螺丝钉展开
Season Two of Command Line Heroes is all about the nuts and bolts that underpin everything we do.
这一讲的英雄是一个女主人公
And this episode's hero is a woman whose journey
如果你想要进一步了解故事 你必须知道她的经历
you need to know if you want to fully understand our reality.
在此给你们隆重介绍：软件界的第一夫人
So, I give you: the first lady of software.
*音效*
*广播音*尊敬的先生们和女士们 我非常荣幸的给你们介绍
Ladies and gentlemen, it's with great pleasure that I present
葛丽丝·玛丽·哈伯Grace Mary Hopper准将
Commodore Grace Mary Hopper.
*鼓掌声*
谢谢
Thank you.
我曾到加拿大的圭尔夫大学演讲
So I went to Canada to speak at the University of Guelph,
那时候我必须在多伦多的机场办理入境手续
and I had to go through immigration at Toronto Airport.
我把护照递给移民官
And I handed my passport to the immigration officer
他打量了护照和我说：“你是在哪里工作的？”
and he looked at it and looked at me and said, "What are you?"
然后我说 “美国海军”
And I said, "United States Navy."
他再次深深的打量我一下
He took a second real hard look at me.
然后他说：“你一定是海军里最老的”
And then he said, "You must be the oldest one they've got."
*欢笑声*
她就是 1985 年担任海军少将的葛丽丝·哈伯
That was Rear Admiral Grace Hopper in 1985.
在麻省理工学院发表了著名的演讲时
She was 79-years old at the time
她 79 岁
and delivering her famous lecture at M.I.T.
即使在那时 她也是一个传奇人物
Even then, Grace Hopper was a legend.
她是独立编程语言之母
She was the god mother of independent programming languages.
实现通过编译器，用人类语言替代数学符号编程这一伟大成就的女性
The woman who used compilers so we could use human language instead of mathematical symbols.
她获得了国家技术奖章
She received the National Medal of Technology,
她去世后(1992 年) 被追授国家自由勋章
and after she died, the National Medal of Freedom.
以上记录纯属真实
So: not a slouch.
他们称她为“神奇葛丽丝”
They called her " Amazing Grace."
如果有人能够被称为天生的程序员
If anybody was born to be a computer programmer,
那么这个人一定是葛丽丝
it was Grace.
这是 Claire Evans
That's Claire Evans,
一个科技记者和《宽带Broad Band》一书的作者
a tech journalist and the author of a book called Broad Band,
而这本书讲述了科技领域的女性先锋
about pioneering women in tech.
Evans 描绘了早期的计算机世界
Evans describes that early word of computers,
在 1940 年 当葛丽丝·哈伯还是一个年轻的女孩时
the one Grace Hopper stepped into in the 1940s
她加入了美军的海军预备役部队
when she was a young woman in the Navy Reserves
当时的电脑有一个小房子那么大
and computers were the size of a small room.
早期的那些程序员
All those early programmers,
他们就像一个圣职者
they were like a priesthood.
他们是一群擅长做枯燥乏味事情的人
They were people that were specifically good at something that was incredibly tedious,
因为那会儿没有编译器
because this is before compilers,
没有编程语言
before programming languages,
人们是确实是一个比特一个比特地对机器编程
when people were really programming at the machine level, bit by bit.
想要改变这种现实
In order to have the constitution to do that kind of thing,
你真的必须是一个特别的人 而葛丽丝真的就是那种人
you really have to be a specific kind of person, and Grace really was that kind of person.
现在，她意识到让人类使用机器语言的是一种多么疯狂的限制
Right away, she saw how crazy limiting it was for humans to be using a language meant for machines.
就像走路的时候 去告诉你身体的每个原子该怎么做
It was like trying to walk down the street by telling every atom in your body what to do.
这是可能的吗？是
Possible? Sure.
效率呢？不高
Efficient? No.
在程序员的意图和计算机的行为之间一定有一条捷径
There had to be a shortcut between a programmer's intentions and a computer's actions.
自从有了算盘 人类一直在将数学思维机械化
Humans had been mechanizing mathematical thinking ever since the abacus.
一定有一种方法可以在计算机上再次实现这一点
There had to be a way to do that again with computers.
在过去 数学家必须做出所有的步骤
In the past, mathematicians used to have to do all this arithmetic.
所有这些枯燥的
All this tedious
一步一步的工作都是为了得到一个真实而有趣的答案
step-by-step work in order to get to the really interesting solutions.
然后有了计算机后 它尽可能地承担了这些机械的运算
And then computers came along and offered the possibility of doing that arithmetic by machine,
所以解放了数学家去进行高层面的、更智慧的、面向系统的思考
therefore freeing the mathematician to think lofty, intellectual, systems-oriented thoughts.
只不过 事实并没有如此发展
Except for, that's not really what happened.
有了计算机 数学家就变成了程序员
Ultimately, the computer came along and then the mathematician had to become a programmer.
他们又一次被这些枯燥无味的编程所束缚
And then they were stuck once again doing all these bit-by-bit tedious rule-oriented,
做着这些一点一滴的繁琐的规则导向的小计算
little calculations in order to write the programs.
因此我认为 葛丽丝的期望是
So, I think, Grace's perspective on it was
她希望计算机能够辅助数学家
she wanted to make sure that computers could assist mathematicians
然后数学家就可以去更进行宏大的思考 做更伟大的
to think great thoughts and do great things
而不至于让他们陷入细节之中
without bogging them down in the details.
*背景音乐*
葛丽丝也加入了思想家的行列
Hopper was joining a long line of thinkers.
我们都知道 帕斯卡Pascal在 17 世纪发明了第一台计算器
You've got Pascal in the 17th century with the first calculator.
巴比奇Babbage在 19 世纪发明了分析
You've got Babbage in the 19th century with the analytical engine.
这些伟大的杰作是发明家们解放人类的大脑的创作
There's this big, beautiful line of inventors who want to build things to supercharge the human brain.
这些发明让我们处理数据的能力空前绝后
Things that let us process more data than we could ever manage on our own.
这就是葛丽丝踏入的领域 发明了所有人都认为不可能的东西
That's the lineage Grace Hopper was stepping into when she invented something that everybody thought was impossible.
我觉得葛丽丝的想法是 人们应该用人类语言与计算机沟通
I mean, Grace's idea that people should be able to communicate with their computers using natural language,
这个语言必须独立于机器的 因此不同计算机可以交互操作
and that language should be machine independent, therefore interoperable between different computing machines
这在当时是革命性的
was revolutionary in its time.
早期她称这个为 “自动化编程”
People that got behind her, this notion that she called, in the early days, "automatic programming,"
在程序员和计算机人的群体中 被认为是像太空学员一样
were considered to be like space cadets in the community of programmers and computer people.
而那些迟迟不上岸的人们被看成了尼安德特人
And the people who weren't onboard eventually became known as the Neanderthals,
这在当时是计算机界的一个巨大的分歧
it was this huge rift in the computing community.
*BGM*
葛丽丝要说服她的上级跨越这个分歧并不容易
Hopper did not have an easy time convincing her superiors to cross that rift.
但她认为这是她的责任 她必须尝试
But she saw it as her duty to try.
There's always a line out here.
*葛丽丝的演讲*
That line represents what your boss will believe at that moment in time.
Now, of course, if you step over it, you don't get the budget.
So you have a double responsibility to that line:
don't step over it, but also keep on educating your boss so you move the line further out,
so next time you can go further into the future.
她推动的那个未来 就是我们的现在
That future she pushed toward is our present.
几乎你我依赖的每一种语言都归功于她和她的第一个编译器
Pretty much every language that you and I rely on owes a debt to Hopper and her first compiler.
因此太空学员们活了下来 尼安德特人灭亡了
So that's space cadets “one”, Neanderthals “zero”.
写代码不用数字 而是用人类风格的语言是她的观点
The idea that we could code not with numbers, but with human-style language.
你敲下“执行操作 8”，或“关闭 文件 C”的精简操作
All of a sudden you're typing "Go to Operation 8," or, "Close file C."
才是符合人类习惯的编程
It was programming made human.
葛丽丝独特地意识到 计算将成为改变世界的事情
Grace was uniquely aware of the fact that computing was going to be a world changing thing,
但是如果没有人知道如何接触并使用计算机
but it wasn't going to be a world changing thing
那么它就不会成为改变世界的事情
if nobody understood how to access it or use it.
因此她想确保它对尽可能多的人开放 尽可能多的人可以使用
And she wanted to make sure that it was as open to as many people as possible and as accessible to as many people as possible.
这就需要编程在可理解性和可读性上做一些妥协
And that required a certain level of concession to comprehensibility and readability.
因此最终创造一个编程语言的目标就是给机器提供更多切入点
So ultimately the desire to create programming languages came from wanting to give more points of entry to the machine
让它脱离这个神职 让它的开发面向大众和未来新一代
and taking it away from this priesthood and opening it up to a greater public and a new generation.
我想在这里打断并强调下 Claire 的说法：
I wanna pause here and just underline something Claire said:
现在我们所已知的编程语言 都来源于科技开放的愿望
programming languages as we know them today come from a desire to open the tech up.
这让计算机不再是数学博士们的专属玩具 让编程开发变得更容易
To take it away from a priesthood of math PhDs and make development accessible.
编译器所有工作的本质
The spirit of the compiler that does all that work,
是让程序变得更好理解 更有人性
it's motivated by a sense of empathy and understanding.
Claire 有一个猜测 为什么葛丽丝是做出改变的那个人
Claire's got a theory about why Hopper was the woman to deliver that change.
这与她在二战期间的工作有关
It has to do with Hopper's work during World War II.
她的工作是解决扫雷问题、弹道问题和海洋学问题
She was doing mine sweeping problems, ballistics problems, oceanography problems.
她用很多不同的、交叉的学科
She was applying all of these different, diverse disciplines
来模拟战争里的所有的暴力、混乱和现实的灾难
representing all the violent, chaotic, messy realities of the war
并将他们转化成在 Mark I 计算机上运行的程序
and translating them into programs to run on the Mark I computer.
她知道如何在语言之间去做翻译转换
She knew how to do that translation between languages.
我的意思不是说计算机语言 是人类语言
And I don't mean computer languages, I mean like human languages.
她知道如何倾听一个提出复杂问题的人的意见
She understood how to listen to somebody who was presenting a complex problem,
并尝试理解问题的背景 其信息和所涉及的专业规律
try to understand where they were coming from, what the constraints and affordances of their discipline was
然后将这些转为计算机可以理解的程序
and then translate that into something that the computer could understand.
从这个角度看她如同早期的编译器
In a way she was like the earliest compiler.
就像一个人类版本的编译器
Like, the embodied human compiler
因为她知道你必须理解他们才能满足他们的需求
because she understood that you had to meet people on their level.
编译器干的事情就是一个解释和理解
Compiling as an act of empathy and understanding.
我觉得我们应该在学习新语言
I think we can all keep that in mind when we learn new languages,
或想知道为什么有一些东西根本不能编译的时候牢记这个理念
or wonder why something isn't compiling at all.
编译器的工作就是满足你使用生活中说的语言来编程
The compiler's job should be to meet your language where it lives.
葛丽丝知道人类一旦可以学会讲编程语言
Grace Hopper knew that once humans could learn to speak programming languages,
而编译器可以将我们的意图转换为机器语言
and once compilers began translating our intentions into machine language,
就像为洪水打开了大门一样
well, it was like opening the floodgates.
她知道如果计算机太孤立和太具体
She knew that computing could never develop
就不会发展为一个产业 从而成为改变世界的力量
as an industry, as a world changing force if it was too siloed and too specific.
也就是说计算机的从业者 可以让提出问题的人跟机器直接沟通
And people who were its practitioners couldn't communicate with the people whose problems needed to be put on the machine, so to speak.
因此她真的是一个善于人类语言翻译的专家
So she was really quite expert at that kind of human translation,
至少我是这么想的 这使她有独一无二的机会
which I think, yeah, made her uniquely
去思考和创建编程语言
qualified to be thinking about and creating programming languages.
*BGM*
葛丽丝对英文式数据处理语言的研究最终演变成了 COBOL
Hopper's work on English-style data processing language eventually evolved into COBOL,
它在某种意味上很不错
which is sort of perfect,
因为它不浮华 很适合商务用途
because COBOL is not flashy, it's very down to business,
葛丽丝·哈伯也是这样的人
and so was Grace Hopper.
从某种角度看 她给了我们一个很像她的语言
In a way, she gave us a language that sounded a lot like her.
像葛丽丝一样 COBOL 语言也很长寿
Also like Hopper, COBOL's got longevity.
它现在已经 60 多了
It's still around 60 years later.
*BGM*
葛丽丝的编译器就像一个巴别鱼babelfish
Okay, so Grace Hopper's compilers were like babelfish,
在程序员和机器之间充当翻译
parlaying meaning between programmers and their machines.
不过它们翻译的都是高度概括性的语言
And they were translating things from higher and higher levels of abstraction.
然后 几十年之后 另一个重要的思潮在语言界兴起
Then, a few decades later, we get another crucial ingredient added to the language mix.
想象下画面：自由软件社区在 1980 年出现
So picture this: the free software community took off in the 1980s,
但是 Unix 的替代品 GNU 被开发出来后
but when the Unix alternative, GNU, was created,
却没有任何自由开放的编译器随之出现
there weren't any free and open compilers to go with it.
为了让 GNU 给我们提供一个真正的开源 UNIX 替代品
In order for GNU to give us a real open-source alternative to Unix,
为了让编程语言在开源世界蓬勃发展
in order for programming languages to thrive in the open-source world,
社区需要找来一个格蕾丝·哈伯---我们需要一个开源编译器
the community would need to pull a Grace Hopper — we needed an open-source compiler.
这是 Langdon White 红帽的平台架构师
Here's Langdon White, a platform architect at Red Hat
来讲讲他对这个事情的理解
talking about where things stood.
在 80 年代 你要买一个编译器很轻松就要花上上万块钱
In the 80s, you can still go spend ten grand pretty easily on a compiler.
费用是最大的问题
The free part was a big deal.
我没有多余的钱去给自己买编译器
I don't have an extra ten grand lying around to go buy myself a compiler.
再一个事实是
Plus the fact that
我必须为所有我想要的目标平台买一个对应的编译器
I'd have to buy myself a compiler for every platform I want to target.
那个时代大部分是 Unix 平台 但是细节和风格各不相同
So, in those days it was mostly Unix, but all the different flavors.
因此你就不能买一个
So you wouldn't be able to just buy one,
你需要为不同的架构 不同的供应商购买多个编译器
you would also have to buy multiple for different architectures or different vendors.
Langdon 指出这不仅仅是成本问题
Langdon notes that it was more than just costs at stake.
在一些情况下 对编码工作也带来了问题
In some cases, it was the coding work itself.
大家都没有意识到
People don't realize that
你如何用很特殊的方式来组织你的代码是很重要的
it matters how you structure your code in very specific ways.
做嵌套 for 循环或者做嵌套 while 循环之类的事情
So doing nested for loops or doing nested while loops or that kind of thing
可能是可以的 这取决于编译器
may be okay, depending on the compiler.
因此 大家都应该明白
So, you know,
如果你不知道编译是如何优化你的代码的
if you don't know how it's optimizing your code
就很难知道如何写出最优的代码
it's very, very difficult to know how to write your code to get the most optimization.
必须要提的是
Suffice to say,
我们需要一个免费的、可获得的、可值得信赖的编译器
we needed a free option, an accessible option, a trustworthy option.
这就是 GNU C 语言编译器：GCC
What we needed was the GNU C compiler, the GCC.
它横空出世在 1987 年
That was the beast, first released in 1987,
它是格蕾丝·哈伯的编译器革命和自由软件运动的结合
that merged Grace Hopper's compiler revolution with the free software movement.
它是使编译更标准化
It standardized things
从而让所有人可以编译别人写的代码
and let everybody compile what anybody else had written.
我们编程语言的丰富性要归功于它
The richness of our languages is thanks to that moment.
GCC 是开放的 可以说将编程语言推向一个更高的层次
The fact that the GCC was open sort of moved languages to a different level.
这是 Jupiter 项目成员 Carol Willing
Carol Willing works at Project Jupiter,
她是 Python 软件基金会的前理事
and she's the former director of the Python Software Foundation.
人们开始意识到
People started realizing that
专有的语言会在特定时间内被服务于一个目的
proprietary languages, while they served a purpose at the time,
但并不能得到开发者社区的认可和热爱
they weren't going to gain the acceptance and adoration of the developer community.
因为如果你是一个开发者
Because if I'm a developer,
你希望学习最常用的 以及未来最流行的东西
I'm going to want to learn what is most commonly used and as well as what is new and on the forefront.
我没必要去发展一种将我锁定在一种技术上的技能
I don't necessarily want to develop a skill that will lock me into one technology.
我想 Python 成功的一个原因是
I think one of the reasons that Python was so successful is
因为它是开源的 它有非常简洁的语法
it was open source, it had a very clean syntax.
它的特点就是允许人们用常见的方法 快速高效地解决问题
What it was doing is it was allowing people in a common way to solve problems quickly, efficiently.
也允许大家合作解决问题
And to also allow people to collaborate.
这就是好的程序和代码库的标志：
And I think those are the signs of good programs and good libraries is:
如果你可以用最小的工作量完成你的工作
if you can get your work done with a minimum amount of headache
并且与他人分享
and you can share it with others.
这是确实很棒的事情
I think that's golden.
这么多年过去了
Over the years,
GCC 逐渐的支持了 Java、C++、Ada 和 Fortran 语言
the GCC evolved to support Java, C++, Ada, Fortran,
我还可以继续说说它的进步
I could go on.
通过像 GCC 这样的通用底层接口
By having a common underlying interface like the GCC,
人们可以根据自己的特殊需求来定制语言
it lets people take languages and then customize them to their particular needs.
例如 在 Python 的世界里
For example, in the Python world,
有大量的库 甚至具体到科学 Python 世界里
there's many different libraries and even specifically in the scientific Python world,
我们有 numpy
we've got things like numpy,
还有 scikit-image、scikit-learn 这样的东西
and scikit-image, scikit-learn.
每个库都是为一个特定目的而工作
And each of those had sort of a more specific task that they are known for.
因此 我们也看到了生物信息学和自然语言处理之类的东西
So, we've also seen things like bioinformatics and natural language processing.
而人们可以在一个共同的基础上 做出很多不同的事情
And so people are able to do many different things working off a common base.
而且可以把它们放到编程语言或库里
But then putting elements into their languages or libraries
使他们能够在他们特定的行业或领域中优化问题的解决
that allow them to optimize problem solving in their particular industry or area.
因此 这就是编译器技术一头撞进开源运动的结果吧？
So, this is what happens when compiler technology runs headfirst into the open source movement, right?
随着时间的推移 这种不同技术的碰撞
Over time, the collision creates a big bang
爆炸般地创造了一个新的、被社区支持的语言
of new community-supported languages
大家都可以学习和完善它
that anybody can learn and build with.
现在有成百上千的编程语言存活着
There are hundreds and hundreds of those languages being used today.
随着开源软件越来越流行和被广泛接受
As open source became more popular and more accepted,
我们看到了编程语言的大量激增
what we've seen is a proliferation of languages.
现在有大量围绕着手机技术的编程语言
There are a number of languages around cell phone technology and mobile.
不同的编程语言也让游戏开发更加简单快速便捷
Different languages that help make game development more straightforward.
各种用途的语言
All purpose languages,
如 Python 和 Ruby
like Python and Ruby
它们算是现代网页开发和交付网页应用和网站的基础
that were sort of foundational for the web development and delivery of web applications and websites.
*BGM*
这个队伍还会继续壮大
The list goes on.
是的 我们建造的这个巴别塔在未来会更加拥挤
And, yeah, that Tower of Babel we're building is just going to get more packed in the future.
但是你可以把它当作一个聚宝盆 一个语言的盛宴
But look, you can also see it as a cornucopia, a language feast.
下面我们将会帮你们梳理这个盛宴
And we're going to help you sort through that feast — next.
*BGM*
现在我们已经知道编程语言泛滥的原因了
Okay, so I know where the language flood came from.
但是这些对我们有什么具体的意义？
But how do we make sense of it all?
我们如何选择对我们重要的语言呢？
How do we pick out languages that matter to us?
*BGM*
这是个大问题，因此我们找了一些人帮忙：
It's a big question, so I brought in some help:
Clive Thompson 是最好的作家之一
Clive Thompson's one of the best writers out there
他能让科技世界变得更有意义
for making sense of the tech world.
他是《连线》的专栏记者
He's a columnist at Wired,
《纽约时报》杂志的特约撰稿人
a contributing writer at the New York Times Magazine,
他现在正在写一本关于计算机程序员心理学的书
and he's working on a book now about the psychology of computer programmers.
当我们挑选我们想要学习的编程语言时
Which is perfect, because we need to know what's going on in our brains
我们需要知道我们到底想要什么
when we choose which ones to learn.
这是我和 Clive 反复讨论得出的结论
Here's me and Clive hashing it all out.
*BGM*
当我作为一个开发新人第一次入手的时候
When I was first starting out as a new developer,
我就说：“让我选一个最好的编程语言
I just said, "Lemme find the best one,
然后掌握并熟练运用它 不就完事了么 ”
I'm going to get really good at it. And then I'll be done."
不过事情不会这样简单
But it's not quite that simple.
否则为什么有那么多的编程语言呢？
Why are there so many programming languages?
每个语言都有那么点它的特长
Each language has sort of a bias of things that it's good at.
因此通常来说
So, typically,
有人创造一个新语言是因为
the reason that someone creates a new language is
现有的语言满足不了他们的需求
there's something they want to do that existing languages aren't good for.
JavaScript 就是一个典型的例子
JavaScript is a good example of that.
网景公司Netscape
Netscape
曾经在 90 年代中开发了一款浏览器
had created a browser back in the mid '90s
所有的网站管理员想做一些更具交互性的事情
and all these web masters wanted to do something a little more interactive.
他们希望有一种方法
They wanted there to be a way
使其可以在网站上运行一些脚本
to have a bit of scripting inside their website.
当然这些需求都提给了网景
And so these demands were coming to Netscape.
然后他们说：“好吧，现在我们没有可以做到这一点的办法
And they were like, "Alright, we need, there's nothing out there that can do this,
我们需要一个可以集成到我们浏览器的脚本语言。”
we need a scripting language that we build inside our browser."
于是他们雇佣了 Brendan Eich
And so they hired Brendan Eich,
一个被认为很资深的家伙
who was considered a senior guy.
他当时 32 岁 其他人 21 岁的样子
He was like 32, and everyone else was like 21.
*Saron Yitbarek的笑声*
这在开发者圈里就很资深了
That's senior in developer world.
他们给他 10 天时间开发 JavaScript
And they gave him ten days to make JavaScript.
因此他真的就 10 天没有睡觉
So he literally just didn't sleep for ten days
然后疯狂地捣鼓出一个脚本语言
and he frantically cranked out a scripting language.
它看起来有点挫 有点糟
And it was kind of ungainly and kind of a mess.
但是可以运行
But it worked.
它允许人们做一些简单的事情
And it allowed people to do very simple things,
它还有按钮 对话框 弹框和其他东西
it had buttons and dialogs and popups and whatnots.
这就是造一个编程语言的例子
And so that's an example of a language that came,
用来做在当时没有办法完成的事情
was created to do something that wasn't really possible at that point in time.
是不是很有意思
That's fascinating.
这就是为什么存在这么多编程语言
So that's why so many languages exist,
人们不断进取 去做别人做不到的事
is that people keep on finding a reason to do something that no one else can do.
这也是为什么我对开发者和编程语言之间的关系很感兴趣
So what is so interesting to me about the relationship between developers and our programming languages
我们对这些工具有很强的依赖性
is we have such a strong attachment to these tools,
为什么呢？
why is that?
有几个原因
There's a couple reasons why.
一个是有时你学习你的第一个编程语言完全是一场意外
One is that sometimes it's literally just an accident of what was the first language that you learned.
有点像你的初恋
And it's kind of like your first love.
我觉得不同性格的人 也会匹配不同类型的编程语言
And I think it's also like different personalities work with different types of languages.
例如 Facebook 是用 PHP 设计的
Like, you look at Facebook, and it was designed using PHP.
PHP 是有点像毛球
And PHP is kind of a hairball of a language.
它很不规则
It's very irregular.
它的成长断断续续
And it sort of grew in these fits and starts.
Facebook 也有点这种感觉
And that's sort of the way Facebook feels, too.
与此相反
In comparison,
来自谷歌的伙计决定：
the guys at Google decided,
“我们想要一个超高性能的语言
"We want a super high performance language,
因为在谷歌我们的东西都高速运行着
because Google, at Google we're all about things running really fast,
维护着万亿级的用户吞吐。”
and things, sustaining trillions of users at once."
因此他们决定开发一个 Go 语言
And so they decide to make Go,
Go 非常适合高性能计算
and Go is a really terrific language for that sort of high-performance computing.
让我们深入一点
Let's go a little bit deeper.
作为一个开发者 我有自己的个性
Is it that I, as a developer, with my specific personality,
我是不是对一部分编程语言有天然的喜欢呢？
am going to be naturally attracted to certain languages?
或者我工作用的编程语言可能会影响我的个性？
Or that the language I work in might influence my personality?
两者肯定都存在
Well, definitely both.
但我确实认为当你遇到你喜欢的编程语言的时候
But I do think that there is a really strong resonance
有一种强烈的共鸣感
that people find when they hit a language that they like.
你上计算机课程时学习了必修语言：
You go to a computer science curriculum and you sort of learn what you have to learn:
他们都教 Java
they're all teaching Java.
有时会多教一门 JavaScript 或 Python
Sometimes more JavaScript or Python.
问题是你被强制要求
But the point is, you're forced to learn it,
所以你学了它
so you learn it.
但当你有选择余地时会怎么样呢？
But what do people do when they have the choice?
这就是你真正看到
And this is where you really see how
一个人的那种情感或心理风格是如何倾向于一门语言的地方
the sort of emotional or psychological style of someone gravitates towards a language,
因为我和一个人谈过
because I talked to one guy
他试着学了一堆 JavaScript
who tried learning JavaScript a bunch.
这是个看起来有点丑的语言
And it was just sort of, it's kind of an ugly language to look at.
它简直是花括号的噩梦
It's got the curly bracket nightmare going on.
所以他试了又试 试了又试 失败了又失败
And so he tried and failed and tried and failed and tried and failed.
直到有一天他看到朋友在用 Python
And then one day he saw a friend working in Python.
在他看起来 这是多么的纯净和美妙的语言
And it just looked so clean and beautiful to him.
因为他是个作家
He was kind of a writer,
而 Python 被认为是一个书写型的编程语言
and it's often regarded as a writerly type of a language,
缩进使一切都易于阅读
because the indentation makes everything easy to read.
它和他一拍即合
And it just clicked with him,
主要在于 Python 的工作方式和外观
because there was just something about the way that Python worked and looked,
漂亮的排版打动了他
it's beautiful sparseness, that hit him.
*BGM*
和 Clive 的交流让我意识到
So, talking with Clive I realized
有一些编程语言是硬塞给我们的
there are languages that are thrust upon us.
我说的是那些古老的编程语言
I'm talking about those ancient languages
已经类似于拉丁语了
that are just baked into everything we work with — the code Latin.
其实我们也有很多选择
But there're also languages we choose,
去选择适合我们个性的编程语言
the languages that fit our personalities.
如果你想知道最新的东西有哪些
And if you want to know what's new and shaking things up,
你去问问开发者们周末在用什么就知道了
you want to ask a developer what they use on the weekend.
下面是我们对话的更多内容：
Here's more of our conversation:
当我问人们：“你闲暇的时候做什么？”
So when I ask people: "What are you doing in your spare time?"
回答肯定是些稀奇古怪的东西
It'll be all this weird stuff.
我想实际上其中一个好的
I think it's actually one of the things that sort of, you know, nice and
最值得称颂的开发者的特点
laudatory about developer behavior
就是他们是富有好奇心
is that they tend to be very curious people.
我知道有人会说
I know people that decided,
“我要学习 Erlang了，就是为了好玩。”
"I'm going to learn Erlang, just for the hell of it."
我尝试想象人们在周末开发这些项目
I'm trying to imagine these projects that people are working on on the weekends.
项目不是最重要的
And it's almost like the project is secondary.
他们在学习工具
It's like the learning of the tool,
编程语言才是重要的事情
the language, is more important.
这才是他们真的想要的状态
That's really what they're there for.
确切的说
Exactly.
你将看到为什么大家不停的
This, is sort of why you'll see people just constantly re-iterating over and over again
重复迭代开发这些日历和待办事项
these calendaring and to-do list things
因为这是一个快速的学习方法
because it's a very quick way,
但需要指出的是
just to figure out, yeah,
编程语言做了什么以及如何工作
what does this language do and how does it work
都与我们没关系
and it almost doesn't matter what I'm building,
我只需要尽可能的构建我的东西
so long as I'm building something.
他们想知道用那样的编程语言思考是什么感觉
They want to know what it feels like to think in that language.
是不是会感觉很轻松、刺激、游刃有余？
Is it going to be, is it going to feel easy, and thrilling and fluent
我目前的使用的语言没这个感觉
that I'm not experiencing with the current languages?
是不是入门之后一切事情都变得简单了？
Is it going to open up doors to make things easier to do?
很有可能你遇到一个新语言后会非常兴奋
So there's a possibility space that occurs when you encounter a new language that can be really exciting.
想起来都很兴奋
Imaginatively exciting.
我是一个 Ruby 从业者
So I'm a Ruby,
作为 Ruby on Rails 开发者我非常自豪
a very proud Ruby on Rails developer,
我想大概是两年前
I think it was about two years ago
另一个非常著名的 Ruby 开发者
that another pretty well known Ruby developer,
Justin Serrals 做了一个非常好的演讲
Justin Serrals, did this really great talk
倡导编程语言从实用角度出发 没有必要那么性感
advocating for this idea that a language doesn't need to be sexy to be used.
他的观点是
And his thesis, his whole point was that
Ruby 之所以是一个令人兴奋的编程语言的原因在于它很新
Ruby was really exciting because it was new.
而且差不多几年前都已经得到印证了
And it kind of got to a point about a couple years ago
它已经不需要更新什么了
where it just didn't need any more things.
它已经是一个稳定、成熟的编程语言了
It was done. It was a stable language, it was a mature language
不过因为它的成熟
and, as a result of it being mature,
开发者对它也就不那么兴奋
it's not as exciting for developers.
我们逐步把目光转移到新的花样来了
It's not this new toy to play, and so we kind of slowly moved away from it on to the next shiny thing.
从某个意义上说
So, in a sense,
很有可能我们的好奇心会扼杀了一个编程语言
it's almost our own curiosity that might kill a language,
或者让它变得庸俗
or make it a little more stale,
而这与编程语言本身的好坏没有关系
independent of whether the language is actually good or bad.
我认为这是完全正确的
I think that's absolutely true.
事实上 你看到的开发者这个极度好奇心和自学欲望的特点
In fact, the downside of this deep curiosity and desire to self-educate that you see amongst developers
会让他们不断地寻找新鲜事物
is that they're constantly trying to find the new shiny thing.
并用这种语言
And use that language to replicate things
去复制其他语言已经基本做得很好的东西
that are already basically done pretty well by other languages.
就是这样
So that's that.
是的
Right.
好奇心有好处 同时也是一个陷阱
Curiosity is a benefit and a trap.
是的 说的很好
Yeah, beautifully put.
*BGM*
有时我们的好奇心可能是一个陷阱
Sometimes our curiosity may be a trap.
但是它也是编程语言革命的动力
But it's also the thing that fuels the evolution of languages.
开发每个新编程语言的时候他们会说
Every new language is created because someone said,
“有没有别的可能？”
"What if?"
它们出现的原因在于
They come about
开发人员想要做不一样的事情
because that developer wanted to do something different.
我们想要全新的表达方式
They wanted a whole new way of saying it.
我向你们承诺一些事情
And I'll promise you something.
我想葛丽丝·哈伯想在这儿最后讲两句
I think Grace Hopper deserves a last word here.
在未来 12 个月里
Just during the next 12 months,
你们谁要是说我们一直都是这么做的
any one of you says that we've always done it that way,
我将会瞬间实质化在你的旁边
I will instantly materialize beside you
然后我 24 小时围绕着你
and I will haunt for 24-hours.
我倒是要看看我能不能引起你的注意
And see if I can get you to take another look.
我们不能再相信那句话
We can no longer afford that phrase,
这是很危险的
it's a dangerous one.
*鼓掌声&BGM*
葛丽丝的故事和第一款编译器提醒我们
The story of Grace Hopper and the first compiler reminds us that
只要能可以找到表达方法
that there's always a better way to do something
我们总有更好的办法做事情
if we can just find the words.
不管编程语言有多抽象
And, no matter how abstract those languages become,
不管我们在机器的 1 和 0 高位还是低位浮动
whether we're floating high or low over the ones and zeroes of machine language,
我们都需要确保它是一个明智选择
we need to make sure it's a smart choice.
我们选择一个语言
We choose the language,
是让它帮助我们的想法更容易表达出来
or maybe even build the language that helps our intentions come closer to reality.
*BGM*
如果你想更深一步学习编程语言和和编译器
If you want to learn more about languages and compilers,
你不会很孤独
you are not alone.
我们收集了一些很有用的文档帮你深入学习
We pulled together some super useful material to help you dive deeper.
敬请在我们节目下面留言
And it's all waiting for you in our show notes.
请查看 redhat.com/commandlineheroes
Check it out at redhat.com/commandlineheroes.
下一期节目 我们将关注开源贡献者的艰辛之路
Next episode, we're tracking the complicated path toward making open-source contributions.
那些维护者的真实奋斗生活是什么样的？
What are the real life struggles of maintainers?
我们如何提出第一个拉取请求？
How do we make that very first pull request?
我们将带你们简单认识开源贡献
We're taking you through Contributing 101.
*BGM*
代码英雄是红帽的原创播客
Command Line Heroes is an original podcast from Red Hat.
你可以在苹果播客、谷歌播客
Listen for free on Apple Podcasts, Google Podcasts,
以及其他可能的地方免费收听这个节目
or wherever you do your thing.
我是 Saron Yitbarek
I'm Saron Yitbarek,
坚持编程 下期再见
until next time keep on coding.
*ED*